Phil: Most often tends to be a
noise - either hypersensitive or
hyposensitive . I used to support a young
man, and he would have ear defenders
because we had the impression he was,
and he was, fairly hypersensitive.
Let me get this right way
around, hypersensitive to noise.
So used the ear defenders for that, but
then would make a lot of noise himself.
Very often, he would be the loudest
in the room, but the difference there
is, I suppose a logic there is, he
was, you had the air defenders, not
only to sort of lessen the sound,
the impact of the sound in his
environment, but also for the physical
sensory input of the pressure as well.
And in terms of him being the
loudest that's a sound, that's
a noise he can control, he can
control his own noise level.
So there was less anxiety on that part,
but then was still hypersensitive to
the noise of others in his environment.
Kerry: There's a hypersensitivity to
sound for two learners in my classroom,
and there's the use of air defenders
and noise thermometers, and we've got
strategies put in place for what we
can do if the classroom's too loud,
but on the flip side of that, they
themselves quite enjoy making loud sounds.
It's when it's an unexpected
sound that we're not too keen.
And we find that just
a little bit too much.
We make sure that our classroom is as
much as possible a quiet environment.
So there's no unnecessary
noises being made.
So, you know, the staff team aren't
chatting to each other about what they
ate for tea last night or what they did at
the weekend, because that's unnecessary.
So it's trying to make sure
that the environment is as
accomodating as possible.
Zoe T: Most of the pupils that
our school will have hypo or
hyper sensory sensitivities, yeah.
Well usually what happens is that
that person becomes, if they're
hypersensitive to something like
hyperacusis, for example, the person
would become emotionally overwhelmed
and need to withdraw or would have
some kind of potentially an emotional
outburst or some people may get
violent in those kinds of situations.
And people who are hyposensitive, that can
be difficult because you don't necessarily
know what's kind of going on for them.
So yes, those sorts of things can
be a major obstacle to learning, to
communicating, to interacting and need to
be really well understood by the people
that are supporting the autistic person
who's experiencing any of those in order
for that person to be able to participate
in whatever it is they're trying to do.